Mathew Tomberlin

AR/VR Developer and Gameplay Engineer

Phone: (209) 338-7200

Email: mathew.tomberlin@gmail.com

Portfolio: https://mathewtomberlin.github.io

Summary

AR/VR Software Engineer and Game Developer with 8+ years of experience

AR/VR developer with a specialty in advanced peripherals like tracking gloves, haptic gloves, and XR headsets. I built a haptic VR game that won AWE 2024's Best in Show, I've published a paper about new VR input methods, and I developed a therapeutic game for a PHD thesis. I also present VR demos for investors and conferences and design testing software for AR/VR hardware. Previously, I served as a Korean linguist and signals intelligence operator in the US Marine Corps.

Skills

- Game Engines: Unity and Unreal Engine
- Rendering: Shaders, Materials, Textures, Lighting
- Code: C#, C++, Blueprints, HLSL, OpenXR
- Gameplay: Physics, combat, AI, level design
- AR/VR Hardware (Oculus, Vive, Index)
- Hand/Body Tracking (Magnetic, bend, IR sensors)
- Optimization and Debugging
- 3D Modeling & Animation

Professional Experience

HaptX Inc.

VR Software Engineer Mar 2022 - Oct 2024

- Shipped a VR game that won AWE 2024's Best of Show that showcased the new G1 haptic tracking gloves
- Shipped AR glove validation software still used by HaptX G1 glove assemblers at Advanced Input Systems (AIS)
- Optimized VR demo framerate by 100% via performance profiling and by debugging engine settings
- Enabled \$12 mil AIS investment and a Y-12 partnership by fixing broken tracking sensors for investor demos
- Gave 100+ VR demos to VIPs, including board members, HaptX investors, and ITSEC 2023 attendees
- Lectured to a CalPoly medical technology class on VR, AR, XR, haptics, and digital twins

Tapestry Solutions, a Boeing company

Software Engineer May 2019 -Mar 2022

- Developed Boeing ESI's internal simulation data processing using Apache Kafka
- Developed the ICODES Load Planner web app via requirements designed by government customers

Undergraduate Researcher

Game Developer Jan 2017 - Mar 2018

- Shipped Scalebridge, a VR game using an EEG headset, that was presented at VS-Games 2019 (PDF) Scalebridge: Adaptive Reasoning Proportional Reasoning Game
- Developed Gauntlet, a VR input technique for hand tracking, and published a paper about it at IEEE VR 2017 (PDF) Gauntlet: Travel Technique for Immersive Environments

US Marine Corps

Korean Linguist and Sigint Operator Oct 2007 - Jun 2012

• Graduated from DLI, Monterey Bay with fluency in Korean and deployed operating intelligence equipment

Personal Projects

Block Breakout

Open-source UE4 C++ Game Oct 2018 -Nov 2018

• Unreal Engine 4 game developed with C++ as open-source project hosted on GitHub Source Code: https://github.com/MathewTomberlin/Breakout

Open Ocean VR

Immersive Underwater VR Game Jan 2018 - Apr 2018

 Designed Unity tools for game designers, modeled and animated animals, and coded the creature behaviors Non-VR Version: https://gamejolt.com/games/OpenOcean/383524

Just One Night

2017 IEEE VR Gauntlet Technique VR Demo Jan 2017 - Mar 2017

• VR game with Leap Motion IR hand-tracking as demo of the Gauntlet VR technique, with art from Polish artists VR & Leap Motion Version: https://studentgames.itch.io/just-one-night

Education

CSU Monterey Bay Computer Science B.S. & Game Programming Concentration Aug 2016 - May 2018